Washington Family Papers
Washington Family Papers
1787-1925
Washington family.
3 linear ft.
Collection consists of business records, correspondence, financial material, and legal records.
3175654
Biographical History
Augustine Washington (1694-1743) was a Virginia planter and the father of George Washington (the first president of the United States). He had a total of ten children by two wives. His son Augustine II (1720-1762) had six children, one of which was William Augustine (1757-1810). William Augustine had nine children by two of his three wives. One of his children, Sarah Tayloe Washington (1800-1886) married a Lawrence Washington (1791-1875), whose relationship to William Augustine's family is unknown. Lawrence is featured prominently in the collection, as is his and Sarah's son Henry Augustine (H.A.) Washington (1820-1858). Several other Washingtons appear frequently in the collection, such as Richard and Robert, however it is uncertain where they fall (if at all) in Augustine Washington's lineage.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Washington Family Papers contain business records, correspondence, miscellaneous financial materials, legal records, and subject files relating to several members of the Washington family.
Business records consist of general records, invoices, receipts, and miscellaneous items.
Correspondence consists of letters sent to members of the Washington family, as well as individual members' outgoing correspondence (for example, Lawrence Washington).
Financial materials consist of vouchers, checks, and receipts.
Legal records consist of an administrator's bond, deeds/deeds of sale, and miscellaneous items.
Subject files include State Department documentation, an account from Washington Irving, correspondence regarding the Freemasons from 1925, and a photograph of Henry Clay Hines.
Most of the collection spans the 1800s, with a few exceptions from the late 1700s and the 1920s.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged in alphabetical order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Washington family.; Virginia -- History.; Business records.; Correspondence.; Deeds.; Financial records.; Invoices.; Legal documents.; Receipts (financial records)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1966, 1969.
Inventory
- Business records
  - General
    - Washington, H.A., 1842-1843; 1847 (Box 1)
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1818; 1828-1832; 1836-1844 (Box 1)
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1810; 1822,; 1829-1830,; 1832,; 1836-1839 (Box 3)
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1843; 1846,; 1850-1854,; 1858,; 1863,; 1870,; 1890,; 1898 (Box 3)
    - Washington, Richard, 1855; 1861,; 1872,; undated (Box 1)
    - Washington, R.J., 1836; 1846,; 1870-1871,; 1880-1884,; 1891 (Box 3)
  - Invoices
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1839; 1846,; 1853-1854,; 1856,; 1859-1861 (Box 1)
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1853 (Oversize 1)
    - Washington, Richard, 1853 (Box 1)
    - Washington, Robert, 1868; 1871,; 1873,; 1879-1883,; 1888-1892,; 1895-1898 (Box 1)
  - Receipts
    - Washington, H.A., 1840-1848; 1855,; 1871 (Box 1)
    - Washington, H.A., 1868; undated (Box 3)
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1844-1858; 1861-1864 (Box 1)
    - Washington, Richard, 1853; 1861,; 1870-1872,; 1879-1888,; 1893-1898 (Box 1)
    - Washington, W.A., 1787-1788; 1793,; 1798,; 1805-1806 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous receipts, 1789; 1838-1839,; 1843-1845,; 1849,; 1860,; 1867,; 1873,; 1881-1884; 1894,; undated (Box 1)
  - Survey, 1799 (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1803-1804; 1828,; 1837,; 1840-1846,; 1857,; 1867,; 1872,; 1885-1888,; 1897-1898,; undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Andrews, D.S., 1887 (Box 1)
  - Armory of Company "F", 1896 (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, H.S., 1880 (Box 1)
  - Ashton, George D., 1844; 1848,; 1849 (Box 1)
  - Ashton, Roberta, 1853 (Box 3)
  - Atwater, J., 1860-1861 (Box 1)
  - Atwill, S.B., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Baker, C.C., undated (Box 1)
  - Barker, J.A., 1897 (Box 1)
  - Barton, H.T., 1870 (Box 1)
  - Bayne, William, 1854 (Box 3)
  - Beale, R.H., 1896 (Box 1)
  - Beddoo, R.E., 1902 (Box 1)
  - Bean, James, 1861 (Box 1)
  - Berry, Law. M., 1838-1839 (Box 1)
  - Bowcock, Henry P., 1834 (Box 1)
  - Brayton, Charles, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Bruce, Edwin, 1897 (Box 1)
  - Combs, R. Ford, 1893 (Box 1)
  - Conway, J., 1832 (Box 1)
  - Cook, L.M., 1893 (Box 1)
  - C, misc, 1837; 1847 (Box 1)
  - Daniel, William M., 1899 (Box 1)
  - Davis, C.A., undated (Box 1)
  - Davis, J.H., 1818 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Septimus, 1897 (Box 1)
  - Dean, William, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Deatty, Henry, 1848 (Box 3)
  - DeMotte, A. Hughes, 1897 (Box 1)
  - Dinsmore and Kyle, 1848 (Box 1)
  - Elhart, Joyner and Co., 1897 (Box 1)
  - Ellason, J., 1897 (Box 1)
  - E, misc, 1847; 1858 (Box 1)
  - Forte, E., undated (Box 1)
  - Fox, Harris, undated (Box 1)
  - Fox, V.B., 1892 (Box 1)
  - Ficklen and Brown, undated (Box 1)
  - Frothingham, O.B., 1862 (Box 1)
  - Gant, B.E., 1837 (Box 3)
  - Garnett, H.T., 1846 (Box 1)
  - George, Sam, 1851 (Box 1)
  - Gilmer, Thomas W., 1893 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin, A., 1847-1851; 1855,; 1857 (Box 2)
  - Griffith, D.H., 1893 (Box 2)
  - Hamlin, Edward O., 1860-1861 (Box 2)
  - Harrison, J., 1836 (Box 2)
  - Hayes, Josiah, 1890 (Box 2)
  - Heath, J., 1838 (Box 2)
  - Hillyer, Wm. P., 1861; 1864 (Box 2)
  - Hindman, William, 1839 (Box 2)
  - Hooper, Frank B., 1899 (Box 2)
  - Horner, H.J., 1902 (Box 3)
  - Hughes, Sam, 1870 (Box 2)
  - Hungerford, M.E., 1830; 1850,; 1896 (Box 2)
  - Hunt, J. Warren, 1891; 1902 (Box 2)
  - Hunter, J., 1840 (Box 2)
  - Hunter, Warrin, 1900 (Box 3)
  - H, misc, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Jackson, R.S., 1848 (Box 2)
  - Jas. F. Carlin's Sons & Company, 1900; 1901 (Box 2)
  - Jett, John J., 1870 (Box 2)
  - Johnston, J. E., 1883; 1889 (Box 2)
  - Jones, W.A., 1891 (Box 2)
  - Killogg, Wm., 1842 (Box 2)
  - King, J.O., 1894 (Box 2)
  - Kyle, D., 1851 (Box 2)
  - Lambson, C.C., 1899 (Box 2)
  - Latawe, William C., 1897 (Box 2)
  - Leigh, Wm., 1894 (Box 2)
  - Lelance, L.A.M., 1838 (Box 3)
  - Lewis, R.B., 1837; 1860,; 1880 (Box 2)
  - Lewis, U., 1897 (Box 2)
  - Lloyd, John, 1838-1839; 1849 (Box 2)
  - Lomax, Thomas, 1801 (Box 2)
  - Marbury, Leonard, 1895 (Box 2)
  - Marmaduke, Wm. M., 1897 (Box 2)
  - Marshall, Henry M., 1899 (Box 2)
  - Mason, J., 1870 (Box 2)
  - Mason, T.A., 1832; 1839,; 1846,; 1848 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, W.T., 1858; 1897 (Box 2)
  - McCulloh, James Wm., 1835 (Box 2)
  - McKenhee, Lambert, 1838 (Box 2)
  - Mercantile-Railway Building and Loan Association, 1894 (Box 2)
  - M, misc, 1849; 1868,; 1893 (Box 2)
  - Neall, W., 1861 (Box 2)
  - Ninde, Frederick F., 1834 (Box 2)
  - Norris, [illegible], 1856 (Box 2)
  - Northern Central Railway, 1897; Glanville, R.B. (Box 2)
  - Office of Virginia Sentinel, 1861 (Box 2)
  - Park, James, 1800 (Box 2)
  - Parker, P., 1898 (Box 2)
  - Patton, Hugh M., 1838-1839 (Box 2)
  - Payne, C.N., 1880 (Box 2)
  - Penniman, James H., 1925 (Box 2)
  - Pope, J.S., 1898 (Box 2)
  - Randall & Randall, 1900 (Box 2)
  - Reardon, [illegible], 1839 (Box 2)
  - Reed, W.B., 1880 (Box 2)
  - Roberts, M., 1836; 1838,; 1844,; 1846-1847 (Box 2)
  - Robinson's Sons, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Rollins, George, 1897 (Box 2)
  - Rose, R.H., 1861 (Box 2)
  - Ryland & Brooks Lumber Co., 1892 (Box 2)
  - Saughton, Lawrence, 1870 (Box 2)
  - Simms, [illegible], 1797 (Box 2)
  - Spillman, C.B., 1904 (Box 2)
  - Staff, W.W., 1897 (Box 2)
  - Stewart, Wm. P., 1836-1837 (Box 2)
  - Storke, E., undated (Box 2)
  - S, misc, 1836 (Box 2)
  - Taggart, [unknown], 1895 (Box 2)
  - Tennent, Anna S., 1838; 1840,; 1842,; 1845 (Box 2)
  - Turner, George J., 1808-1809 (Box 2)
  - Unidentifiable, 1836-1839; 1843,; 1848-1850 (Box 3)
  - Vausant, George, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Virginia Trust Company, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Charles R., 1888 (Box 2)
  - Washington, Bushrod C., 1907 (Box 2)
  - Washington, George, undated; Sent to G. Washington (Box 2)
  - Washington, George, 1832; 1837-1839,; 1848-1850,; 1854-1858,; 1861,; 1866 (Box 3)
  - Washington, George, 1799; Photostat (Box 3)
  - Washington, G.C., 1825; 1873,; undated (Box 2)
  - Washington, John, 1899 (Box 2)
  - Washington, J.B., 1889 (Box 2)
  - Washington, J.E., 1854 (Box 2)
  - Washington, J.M., 1830 (Box 2)
  - Washington, Lawrence, 1815; 1819,; 1838-1843,; 1850-1854,; 1857-1859,; 1863,; 1891,; 1894,; undated (Box 2)
  - Washington, Lloyd, 1870; 1896,; 1899 (Box 2)
  - Washington, Richard, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Washington, R., 1852 (Box 3)
  - Washington, R.J., 1892-1893; 1901-1902 (Box 2)
  - White, A.P., 1853 (Box 2)
  - Whitehouse, E.B., 1892 (Box 3)
  - Willink, John A., 1818 (Box 2)
  - Wirt, D.C., 1858-1859 (Box 2)
  - Withers, Edmund, 1800 (Box 2)
  - White & Jacob, 1870 (Box 2)
  - Wilson, J.F., 1860 (Box 2)
  - Zollickoffer, D.C., 1892 (Box 2)
  - Misc, envelopes, 1898-1900; undated (Box 2)
  - Misc, unidentifiable, 1837; 1847,; 1851-1854,; 1870,; 1892,; 1896,; 1898 (Box 3)
- Financial materials
  - Miscellaneous, 1838; 1846,; 1892,; 1896,; undated (Box 2)
- Legal records
  - Administrators Bond, 1861; Richard Washington (Box 2)
  - Deeds
    - Maiden, R.H., 1895 (Box 2)
    - Washington, H.T., 1894 (Box 3)
    - Washington, Lawrence, 1883; 1887 (Box 3)
    - Washington, Robert J., 1883-1884 (Box 3)
  - Pleas
    - Stuart, R.H., 1888; 1893 (Box 3)
    - Washington, Law., 1857 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1830; 1843,; 1847,; 1854-1855,; 1873,; 1894-1895,; undated (Box 2)
- Subject files
  - State Department documentation, 1900; Jane B. Washington (Oversize 1)
  - Irving, Washington, undated; a document addressing Washington Irving's account of a Washington's religious activities (Box 2)
  - Masons, 1925; correspondence involving debates about President George Washington's alleged loyalty to the Freemasons (Box 2)
  - Photograph, undated; a photograph of Henry Clay Hines and George Washington's check (Box 3)